Finding Aid for Verner Winslow Crane Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Verner Winslow Crane Papers
1911-1974
Crane, Verner Winslow, 1889-
851030 Ac Aa 2
Professor of early American history at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, files, lecture materials, papers relating to his books and articles, and professional activities, including correspondence with prominent historians.
9 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
No additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Papers, 1911-1974, of Verner W. Crane, professor of history at the University of Michigan; contain correspondence files, lecture materials, papers relating to his books and articles, and professional activities. Correspondents include: John R. Alden, Charles M. Andrews, Herbert E. Bolton, Julian P. Boyd, Carl Bridenbaugh, Ronald S. Crane, Lawrence H. Gipson, Oscar Handlin, Robert A. Humphreys, Bernhard Knollenberg, Edmund S. Morgan, Frederick B. Tolles, Frederick J. Turner, Carl Van Doren, Claude H. Van Tyne, Clarence L. Ver Steeg, and Lawrence C. Wroth.
Subjects:
Crane, Verner W., 1889-1974; Historians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Contributors:
Alden, John Richard, 1908-1991; Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943.; Bolton, Herbert Eugene, 1870-1953.; Boyd, Julian P. (Julian Parks), 1903-1980; Bridenbaugh, Carl.; Crane, Ronald S. (Ronald Salmon), 1886-1967.; Gipson, Lawrence Henry, 1880-1971; Handlin, Oscar, 1915-2011; Humphreys, R. A. (Robert Arthur), 1907-1999; Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973.; Morgan, Edmund Sears.; Tolles, Frederick Barnes, 1915-1975; Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932.; Van Doren, Carl, 1885-1950.; Van Tyne, Claude Halstead, 1869-1930.; Ver Steeg, Clarence Lester, 1922-; Wroth, Lawrence C. (Lawrence Counselman), 1884-1970.
- Correspondence, 1911-
  - A-Az, including Charles M. Andrews, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Alden, John Richard, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - B-Bz, including Herbert E. Bolton, Julian P. Boyd, Carl Bridenbaugh, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Brock, Leslie U., including obituary of Lawrence Henry Gipson, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - C-Cz, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - D-Dz (Box 1)
  - E-Ez (Box 1)
  - F-Fz, including Allyn B. Forbes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - G-Gz, including Lawrence Henry Gipson, Evarts B. Greene (Box 1)
  - H-Hz, including Houghton-Mifflin Company, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Handlin, Oscar (Box 1)
  - Humphreys, Robert Arthur, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - J-Jz (Box 1)
  - K-Kz, including Bernhard Knollenberg, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - L-Lz (Box 1)
  - M-Mz, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Morgan, Edmund S (Box 1)
  - N-Nz (Box 1)
  - O-Oz (Box 1)
    (includes James Osborn; see microfilm of James Osborn -- Verner Crane correspondence)
  - P-Pz (Box 1)
  - R-Rz (Box 1)
  - S-Sz, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - T-Tz, including Frederick B. Tolles, Frederick Jackson Turner (Box 1)
  - U-Uz and V-Vz, including Carl Van Doren, Claude Van Tyne, Clarence Ver Steeg (Box 1)
  - W-Wz, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Wroth, Lawrence C (Box 1)
  - X-Z (Box 1)
- Miscellanea:
  - Family correspondence (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and miscellanea of Ronald S. Crane (Box 2)
  - Memberships (Box 2)
  - Commencement University of Pennsylvania, 1915 (Box 2)
  - Professional appointments, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - American Historical Review Executive Board, 1928-1937; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - American Historical Association Carnegie Revolving Fund, 1939-1941 (Box 2)
  - University College Centenary London, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Mississippi Valley Historical Association nominating committee, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - Harvard University Ad Hoc Committee, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Institute of American History and Culture, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Critique University of Michigan Press, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Center of American Authors project, circa 1966 (Box 2)
  - Bibliography of publications and Franklin bibliography, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and 1969-1973, concerning Benjamin Franklin, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 2)
  - Lettre du Landgrave de Hesse 1777 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Diplomas and citations (Box Ac)
- Lectures and Notes, 1929-1969
  - Rhode Island Historical Society concerning Henry Marchant, 1929; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Brown University Colver lecture, "Benjamin Franklin: Englishman and American", 1935 (Box 2)
  - University College, London Public Lecture,"Benjamin Franklin and the British Empire", 1938 (Box 2)
  - The Franklin Institute "Franklin Is Political Journalism in England", 1939 (Box 2)
  - Notes Thomas Bray's Will and the Reorganization of the Associates, circa 1942 (Box 2)
  - C.B.S. The Invitation to Learning, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Commemorative luncheon 249th anniversary of Franklin's birth, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Friends of the Detroit Public Library "Benjamin Franklin, author", 1956 (Box 2)
  - The University of Michigan Russel Lecture, "Dr. Franklin's Plan for America", 1958 (Box 2)
  - Bryn Mawr "Benjamin Franklin and the Political Journalism of the Eighteenth Century", 1958 (Box 2)
  - State University Teachers College, New Platz, New York Convocation address, "Franklin, the New Yorkers, and the Albany Congress", 1959 (Box 2)
  - Mississippi Valley Historical Association annual meeting, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Retirement dinner letters from students, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Dunwurkin Club, ca. 1960s"Benjamin Franklin's Clubs in England, 1758-1775" (Box 2)
  - Dunwurkin Club notes for address, 1969 (Box 2)
  - "The Political Development of the United States,", undated (Box 2)
- Books and Articles:
  - "The West in the Diplomacy of the American Revolution,", 1911 (Box 3)
  - "The Tennessee River as the Road to Carolina: The Beginnings of Exploration and Trade,", 1916 (Box 3)
  - Creek and Westo Indians: "An Historical Note on the Westo Indians," 1918 "The Origin of the Name of the Creek Indians," 1918 "Westo and Chisca," 1919 (Box 3)
  - 'A Lost Utopia of the First American Frontier,", 1919 (Box 3)
  - "The Southern Frontier in Queen Anne's War,", 1919 (Box 3)
  - "The Philanthropist and the Genesis of Georgia", 1921 (Box 3)
  - "Hints Relative to the Division and Government of the Conquered and Newly Conquered Countries in America," discussion of letter to Board of Trade from the Earl of Egremont, 1921 (Box 3)
  - "A Rhode Island Slaver," 1922with introduction by Verner W. Crane (Box 3)
  - "The Promotion Literature of Georgia,", 1925 (Box 3)
  - "Projects for Colonization in the South, 1684-1732", 1925 (Box 3)
  - The Southern Frontier 1670-1732, reviews and notices, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Dictionary of American Biography, 1929-1930, 1932 Edward McCrady, Jr., Henry Woodward, Arthur L. Cross (Box 3)
  - "The Origins of Georgia,", 1930 (Box 3)
  - "Certain Writings of Benjamin Franklin on the British Empire and the American Colonies,", 1934 (Box 3)
  - Benjamin Franklin: Englishman and American reviews, 1936 (Box 3)
  - "Three Tables of Benjamin Franklin,", 1936 (Box 3)
  - "Benjamin Franklin on Slavery and American Liberties,", 1938 (Box 3)
  - "Max Farrand and Benjamin Franklin's Memoirs,", 1949 (Box 3)
  - Benjamin Franklin's Letters to the Press,1950 Correspondence with publishers, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Benjamin Franklin and a Rising People,1954reviews and publisher's correspondence (Box 3)
  - Autobiography of Benjamin Franklin introduction by Verner W. Crane, 1956 (Box 3)
  - "Franklin's Marginalia, and the Lost 'Treatise' on the Empire,", 1957 (Box 3)
  - "Franklin's 'The Internal State of America (1786),"', 1958 (Box 3)
  - "Dr. Thomas Bray and the Charitable Colony Project, 1730", 1962 (Box 3)
  - Article on Benjamin Franklin Colliers Encyclopedia, 1965 (Box 3)
  - "Club of Honest Whigs,", 1966 (Box 3)
  - "Franklin on the Culture of Indian Corn in the Colonies,", circa 1968 (Box 3)
  - Reviews, 1929-1959, by Verner W. Crane (Box 3)
  - Albany Congress Plan of Union controversy with Lawrence Henry Gipson, 1943-1960; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Papers concerning the editing of the Franklin papers, 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Draft, incomplete essay on George Washington (Box 3)
- Lecture notes and course materials
  - American Colonial history to the French and Indian War, 21 folders (Box 3)
  - American Colonial history to the French and Indian War, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - The American Revolution 1754-1789, 44 folders (Box 4)
  - Early Spanish activities in North America (Box 4)
  - Bibliographies and methodology, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Benjamin Franklin research files
  - Topical files (Box 5)
  - Commonwealth Lectures, London, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Biographical materials
    - [A-P] (Box 6)
    - [Q-Z] (Box 7)
  - Biographical materials (Box 7)
  - Chronological notes
    - Pre-1754-1767 (Box 7)
    - B (Box 7)
  - Chronological notes, 1768-post 1776 (Box 8)
  - Bibliography (Box 8)
  - Bibliography (Box 9)
    (continued)